<PRESDOCU>
        <EXECORD>
          <TITLE3>Title 3—</TITLE3>
          <PRES>The President<PRTPAGE P="3137"/>
          </PRES>
          <EXECORDR>Executive Order 13370 of January 13, 2005</EXECORDR>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Providing an Order of Succession in the Office of </HD>
          <LI>Management and Budget</LI>

          <FP>By the authority vested in me as President by the Constitution and the laws of the United States of America and pursuant to the Federal Vacancies Reform Act of 1998, 5 U.S.C. 3345 <E T="03">et seq</E>., it is hereby ordered that:</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Section 1.</E> During any period when the Director of the Office of Management and Budget (Director) and the Deputy Director of the Office of Management and Budget (Deputy Director) have died, resigned, or otherwise become unable to perform the functions and duties of the office of Director, the following officers of the Office of Management and Budget, in the order listed, shall perform the functions and duties of the office of Director, if they are eligible to act as Director under the provisions of the Federal Vacancies Reform Act of 1998, until such time as at least one of the officers mentioned above is able to perform the functions and duties of the office of Director:</FP>
          <P>Deputy Director for Management;</P>
          <P>Executive Associate Director;</P>
          <P>Associate Director (National Security Programs);</P>
          <P>Associate Director (General Government Programs);</P>
          <P>Associate Director (Human Resource Programs);</P>
          <P>Associate Director (Natural Resource Programs);</P>
          <P>General Counsel;</P>
          <P>Administrator for Federal Procurement Policy;</P>
          <P>Administrator of the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs;</P>
          <P>Controller, Office of Federal Financial Management; and</P>
          <P>Administrator of the Office of Electronic Government.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 2.</E>
            <E T="03"> Exceptions.</E> (a) No individual who is serving in an office listed in section 1 in an acting capacity, by virtue of so serving, shall act as Director pursuant to this order.<PRTPAGE P="3138"/>
          </FP>
          <P>(b) Notwithstanding the provisions of this order, the President retains discretion, to the extent permitted by law, to depart from this order in designating an acting Director.</P>
          <PSIG>B</PSIG>
          <PLACE>THE WHITE HOUSE,</PLACE>
          <DATE>January 13, 2005.</DATE>
          <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 05-1170</FRDOC>
          <FILED>Filed 1-18-05; 8:45 am]</FILED>
          <BILCOD>Billing code 3195-01-P</BILCOD>
        </EXECORD>
      </PRESDOCU>