<PRESDOCU>
        <EXECORD>
          <TITLE3>Title 3—</TITLE3>
          <PRES>The President<PRTPAGE P="50909"/>
          </PRES>
          <EXECORDR>Executive Order 13511 of September 29, 2009</EXECORDR>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Continuance of Certain Federal Advisory Committees</HD>
          <FP>By the authority vested in me as President by the Constitution and the laws of the United States of America, and consistent with the provisions of the Federal Advisory Committee Act, as amended (5 U.S.C. App.), it is hereby ordered as follows:</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Section 1.</E> Each advisory committee listed below is continued until September 30, 2011.</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(a) Committee for the Preservation of the White House; Executive Order 11145, as amended (Department of the Interior).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(b) National Infrastructure Advisory Council; Executive Order 13231, as amended (Department of Homeland Security).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(c) Federal Advisory Council on Occupational Safety and Health; Executive Order 12196, as amended (Department of Labor).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(d) President's Board of Advisors on Historically Black Colleges and Universities; Executive Order 13256 (Department of Education).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(e) President's Board of Advisors on Tribal Colleges and Universities; Executive Order 13270 (Department of Education).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(f) President's Commission on White House Fellowships; Executive Order 11183, as amended (Office of Personnel Management).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(g) President's Committee for People with Intellectual Disabilities; Executive Order 12994, as amended (Department of Health and Human Services).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(h) President's Committee on the Arts and the Humanities; Executive Order 12367, as amended (National Endowment for the Arts).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(i) President's Committee on the International Labor Organization; Executive Order 12216, as amended (Department of Labor).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(j) President's Committee on the National Medal of Science; Executive Order 11287, as amended (National Science Foundation).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(k) President's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports; Executive Order 13265 (Department of Health and Human Services).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(l) President's Council of Advisors on Science and Technology; Executive Order 13226, as amended (Office of Science and Technology Policy).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(m) President's Export Council; Executive Order 12131, as amended (Department of Commerce).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(n) President's National Security Telecommunications Advisory Committee; Executive Order 12382, as amended (Department of Homeland Security).</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(o) Trade and Environment Policy Advisory Committee; Executive Order 12905 (Office of the United States Trade Representative).</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 2.</E> Notwithstanding the provisions of any other Executive Order, the functions of the President under the Federal Advisory Committee Act that are applicable to the committees listed in section 1 of this order shall be performed by the head of the department or agency designated after each committee, in accordance with the guidelines and procedures established by the Administrator of General Services.</FP>
          
          <PRTPAGE P="50910"/>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 3.</E> Sections 1 and 2 of Executive Order 13446 are superseded by sections 1 and 2 of this order.</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 4.</E> This order shall be effective September 30, 2009.</FP>
          <GPH DEEP="62" HTYPE="RIGHT" SPAN="1">
            <GID>OB#1.EPS</GID>
          </GPH>
          <PSIG> </PSIG>
          <PLACE>THE WHITE HOUSE,</PLACE>
          <DATE>September 29, 2009.</DATE>
          <FRDOC>[FR Doc. E9-23886</FRDOC>
          <FILED>Filed 9-30-09; 11:15 am]</FILED>
          <BILCOD>BILLING CODE 3195-W9-P</BILCOD>
        </EXECORD>
      </PRESDOCU>