<PRESDOCU>
        <EXECORD>
          <TITLE3>Title 3—</TITLE3>
          <PRES>The President<PRTPAGE P="8497"/>
          </PRES>
          <EXECORDR>Executive Order 13198 of January 29, 2001</EXECORDR>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Agency Responsibilities With Respect to Faith-Based and Community Initiatives</HD>
          <FP>By the authority vested in me as President by the Constitution and the laws of the United States of America, and in order to help the Federal Government coordinate a national effort to expand opportunities for faith-based and other community organizations and to strengthen their capacity to better meet social needs in America's communities, it is hereby ordered as follows:</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Section 1.</E>
            <E T="03"> Establishment of Executive Department Centers for Faith-Based and Community Initiatives.</E> (a) The Attorney General, the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of Labor, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, and the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall each establish within their respective departments a Center for Faith-Based and Community Initiatives (Center).</FP>
          <P>(b) Each executive department Center shall be supervised by a Director, appointed by the department head in consultation with the White House Office of Faith-Based and Community Initiatives (White House OFBCI).</P>
          <P>(c) Each department shall provide its Center with appropriate staff, administrative support, and other resources to meet its responsibilities under this order.</P>
          <P>(d) Each department's Center shall begin operations no later than 45 days from the date of this order.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 2.</E>
            <E T="03"> Purpose of Executive Department Centers for Faith-Based and Community Initiatives.</E> The purpose of the executive department Centers will be to coordinate department efforts to eliminate regulatory, contracting, and other programmatic obstacles to the participation of faith-based and other community organizations in the provision of social services.</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 3.</E>
            <E T="03"> Responsibilities of Executive Department Centers for Faith-Based and Community Initiatives.</E> Each Center shall, to the extent permitted by law: (a) conduct, in coordination with the White House OFBCI, a department-wide audit to identify all existing barriers to the participation of faith-based and other community organizations in the delivery of social services by the department, including but not limited to regulations, rules, orders, procurement, and other internal policies and practices, and outreach activities that either facially discriminate against or otherwise discourage or disadvantage the participation of faith-based and other community organizations in Federal programs;</FP>
          <P>(b) coordinate a comprehensive departmental effort to incorporate faith-based and other community organizations in department programs and initiatives to the greatest extent possible;</P>
          <P>(c) propose initiatives to remove barriers identified pursuant to section 3(a) of this order, including but not limited to reform of regulations, procurement, and other internal policies and practices, and outreach activities;</P>
          <P>(d) propose the development of innovative pilot and demonstration programs to increase the participation of faith-based and other community organizations in Federal as well as State and local initiatives; and</P>

          <P>(e) develop and coordinate department outreach efforts to disseminate information more effectively to faith-based and other community organizations with respect to programming changes, contracting opportunities, and <PRTPAGE P="8498"/>other department initiatives, including but not limited to Web and Internet resources.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 4.</E>
            <E T="03"> Additional Responsibilities of the Department of Health and Human Services and the Department of Labor Centers.</E> In addition to those responsibilities described in section 3 of this order, the Department of Health and Human Services and the Department of Labor Centers shall, to the extent permitted by law: (a) conduct a comprehensive review of policies and practices affecting existing funding streams governed by so-called “Charitable Choice” legislation to assess the department's compliance with the requirements of Charitable Choice; and (b) promote and ensure compliance with existing Charitable Choice legislation by the department, as well as its partners in State and local government, and their contractors.</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 5.</E>
            <E T="03"> Reporting Requirements.</E> (a) Report. Not later than 180 days after the date of this order and annually thereafter, each of the five executive department Centers described in section 1 of this order shall prepare and submit a report to the White House OFBCI.</FP>
          <P>(b) Contents. The report shall include a description of the department's efforts in carrying out its responsibilities under this order, including but not limited to:</P>
          <P> (1) a comprehensive analysis of the barriers to the full participation of faith-based and other community organizations in the delivery of social services identified pursuant to section 3(a) of this order and the proposed strategies to eliminate those barriers; and</P>
          <P> (2) a summary of the technical assistance and other information that will be available to faith-based and other community organizations regarding the program activities of the department and the preparation of applications or proposals for grants, cooperative agreements, contracts, and procurement.</P>
          <P>(c) Performance Indicators. The first report, filed 180 days after the date of this order, shall include annual performance indicators and measurable objectives for department action. Each report filed thereafter shall measure the department's performance against the objectives set forth in the initial report.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 6.</E>
            <E T="03"> Responsibilities of All Executive Departments and Agencies.</E> All executive departments and agencies (agencies) shall: (a) designate an agency employee to serve as the liaison and point of contact with the White House OFBCI; and</FP>
          <P>(b) cooperate with the White House OFBCI and provide such information, support, and assistance to the White House OFBCI as it may request, to the extent permitted by law.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 7.</E>
            <E T="03"> Administration and Judicial Review.</E> (a) The agencies' actions directed by this Executive Order shall be carried out subject to the availability of appropriations and to the extent permitted by law.</FP>
          <P>(b) This order does not create any right or benefit, substantive or procedural, enforceable at law or equity against the United States, its agencies or instrumentalities, its officers or employees, or any other person.</P>
          <PSIG>B</PSIG>
          <PLACE>THE WHITE HOUSE,</PLACE>
          <DATE> January 29, 2001.</DATE>
          <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 01-2851</FRDOC>
          <FILED>Filed 1-30-01; 11:45 am]</FILED>
          <BILCOD>Billing code 3195-01-P</BILCOD>
        </EXECORD>
      </PRESDOCU>