<PRESDOCU>
        <EXECORD>
          <TITLE3>Title 3—</TITLE3>
          <PRES>The President<PRTPAGE P="509"/>
          </PRES>
          <EXECORDR>Executive Order 13857 of January 25, 2019</EXECORDR>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Taking Additional Steps To Address the National Emergency With Respect to Venezuela</HD>

          <FP>By the authority vested in me as President by the Constitution and the laws of the United States of America, including the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1701 <E T="03">et seq.</E>), the National Emergencies Act (50 U.S.C. 1601 <E T="03">et seq.</E>), and section 301 of title 3, United States Code,</FP>
          <FP>I, DONALD J. TRUMP, President of the United States of America, in order to take additional steps with respect to the national emergency declared in Executive Order 13692 of March 8, 2015, and relied upon for additional steps taken in Executive Order 13808 of August 24, 2017, Executive Order 13827 of March 19, 2018, Executive Order 13835 of May 21, 2018, and Executive Order 13850 of November 1, 2018, particularly in light of actions by persons affiliated with the illegitimate Maduro regime, including human rights violations and abuses in response to anti-Maduro protests, arbitrary arrest and detention of anti-Maduro protestors, curtailment of press freedom, harassment of political opponents, and continued attempts to undermine the Interim President of Venezuela and undermine the National Assembly, the only legitimate branch of government duly elected by the Venezuelan people, and to prevent the Interim President and the National Assembly from exercising legitimate authority in Venezuela, hereby order:</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Section 1</E>. (a) Subsection (d) of section 6 of Executive Order 13692, subsection (d) of section 3 of Executive Order 13808, subsection (d) of section 3 of Executive Order 13827, subsection (d) of section 3 of Executive Order 13835, and subsection (d) of section 6 of Executive Order 13850, are hereby amended to read as follows:</FP>
          <P>“(d) the term “Government of Venezuela” includes the state and Government of Venezuela, any political subdivision, agency, or instrumentality thereof, including the Central Bank of Venezuela and Petroleos de Venezuela, S.A. (PDVSA), any person owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by the foregoing, and any person who has acted or purported to act directly or indirectly for or on behalf of, any of the foregoing, including as a member of the Maduro regime.”</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 2</E>. (a) Nothing in this order shall be construed to impair or otherwise affect:</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(i) the authority granted by law to an executive department or agency, or the head thereof; or</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP1">(ii) the functions of the Director of the Office of Management and Budget relating to budgetary, administrative, or legislative proposals.</FP>
          <P>(b) This order shall be implemented consistent with applicable law and subject to the availability of appropriations.</P>
          
          <PRTPAGE P="510"/>
          <P>(c) This order is not intended to, and does not, create any right or benefit, substantive or procedural, enforceable at law or in equity by any party against the United States, its departments, agencies, or entities, its officers, employees, or agents, or any other person.</P>
          <GPH DEEP="80" HTYPE="RIGHT" SPAN="1">
            <GID>Trump.EPS</GID>
          </GPH>
          <PSIG> </PSIG>
          <PLACE>THE WHITE HOUSE,</PLACE>
          <DATE>January 25, 2019.</DATE>
          <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2019-00615 </FRDOC>
          <FILED>Filed 1-29-19; 11:15 am]</FILED>
          <BILCOD>Billing code 3295-F9-P</BILCOD>
        </EXECORD>
      </PRESDOCU>