<PRESDOCU>
        <EXECORD>
          <TITLE3>Title 3—</TITLE3>
          <PRES>The President<PRTPAGE P="31931"/>
          </PRES>
          <EXECORDR>Executive Order 13303 of May 22, 2003</EXECORDR>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Protecting the Development Fund for Iraq and Certain Other Property in Which Iraq Has an Interest</HD>

          <FP>By the authority vested in me as President by the Constitution and the laws of the United States of America, including the International Emergency Economic Powers Act, as amended (50 U.S.C. 1701 <E T="03">et seq</E>.) (IEEPA), the National Emergencies Act (50 U.S.C. 1601 <E T="03">et seq</E>.), section 5 of the United Nations Participation Act, as amended (22 U.S.C. 287c) (UNPA), and section 301 of title 3, United States Code,</FP>
          <FP>I, GEORGE W. BUSH, President of the United States of America, find that the threat of attachment or other judicial process against the Development Fund for Iraq, Iraqi petroleum and petroleum products, and interests therein, and proceeds, obligations, or any financial instruments of any nature whatsoever arising from or related to the sale or marketing thereof, and interests therein, obstructs the orderly reconstruction of Iraq, the restoration and maintenance of peace and security in the country, and the development of political, administrative, and economic institutions in Iraq. This situation constitutes an unusual and extraordinary threat to the national security and foreign policy of the United States and I hereby declare a national emergency to deal with that threat.</FP>
          <FP>I hereby order:</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Section 1.</E> Unless licensed or otherwise authorized pursuant to this order, any attachment, judgment, decree, lien, execution, garnishment, or other judicial process is prohibited, and shall be deemed null and void, with respect to the following:</FP>
          <P>(a) the Development Fund for Iraq, and</P>
          <P>(b) all Iraqi petroleum and petroleum products, and interests therein, and proceeds, obligations, or any financial instruments of any nature whatsoever arising from or related to the sale or marketing thereof, and interests therein, in which any foreign country or a national thereof has any interest, that are in the United States, that hereafter come within the United States, or that are or hereafter come within the possession or control of United States persons.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 2.</E> (a) As of the effective date of this order, Executive Order 12722 of August 2, 1990, Executive Order 12724 of August 9, 1990, and Executive Order 13290 of March 20, 2003, shall not apply to the property and interests in property described in section 1 of this order.</FP>
          <P>(b) Nothing in this order is intended to affect the continued effectiveness of any rules, regulations, orders, licenses or other forms of administrative action issued, taken, or continued in effect heretofore or hereafter under Executive Orders 12722, 12724, or 13290, or under the authority of IEEPA or the UNPA, except as hereafter terminated, modified, or suspended by the issuing Federal agency and except as provided in section 2(a) of this order.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 3.</E> For the purposes of this order:</FP>
          <P>(a) The term “person” means an individual or entity;</P>
          <P>(b) The term “entity” means a partnership, association, trust, joint venture, corporation, group, subgroup, or other organization;</P>

          <P>(c) The term “United States person” means any United States citizen, permanent resident alien, entity organized under the laws of the United <PRTPAGE P="31932"/>States or any jurisdiction within the United States (including foreign branches), or any person in the United States;</P>
          <P>(d) The term “Iraqi petroleum and petroleum products” means any petroleum, petroleum products, or natural gas originating in Iraq, including any Iraqi-origin oil inventories, wherever located; and</P>
          <P>(e) The term “Development Fund for Iraq” means the fund established on or about May 22, 2003, on the books of the Central Bank of Iraq, by the Administrator of the Coalition Provisional Authority responsible for the temporary governance of Iraq and all accounts held for the fund or for the Central Bank of Iraq in the name of the fund.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 4.</E> (a) The Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense, is hereby authorized to take such actions, including the promulgation of rules and regulations, and to employ all powers granted to the President by IEEPA and the UNPA as may be necessary to carry out the purposes of this order. The Secretary of the Treasury may redelegate any of these functions to other officers and agencies of the United States Government. All agencies of the United States Government are hereby directed to take all appropriate measures within their statutory authority to carry out the provisions of this order.</FP>
          <P>(b) Nothing contained in this order shall relieve a person from any requirement to obtain a license or other authorization in compliance with applicable laws and regulations.</P>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 5.</E> This order is not intended to, and does not, create any right, benefit, or privilege, substantive or procedural, enforceable at law or in equity by a party against the United States, its departments, agencies, entities, officers, employees, or agents, or any other person.</FP>
          <FP>
            <E T="04">Sec. 6.</E> This order shall be transmitted to the Congress and published in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E>.</FP>
          <PSIG>B</PSIG>
          <PLACE>THE WHITE HOUSE,</PLACE>
          <DATE>May 22, 2003.</DATE>
          <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 03-13412</FRDOC>
          <FILED>Filed 5-23-03; 11:28 am]</FILED>
          <BILCOD>Billing code 3195-01-P</BILCOD>
        </EXECORD>
      </PRESDOCU>